[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software hi this is Priyanka Ragin for
software engineering radio and today I
have with me Charlie Jones director of
product management at reversing labs and
a subject matter expert in supply chain
security he was formerly a consultant at
P PWC and has about 10 years of
experience delivering strategic
transformative initiatives specializing
in cyber security thirdparty risk
management and it audit programs for
various companies across all the lines
of difference today we are here to
discuss the topic tackling thirdparty
software risks and as you all have
listened to the couple of episodes that
we've done on software supply chain risk
I think this is going to be a very
exciting show so welcome to the show
Charlie thank you very much for having
me I'm excited to dive into third party
risk today okay great is there anything
else that you would like all our
listeners to know about you that I
haven't mentioned no I think you did a
great intro that's that was perfect okay
perfect so let's Jump Right In but first
thing first I thought I'll ask you for
some definitions so what are third party
software risks are they commercial off
the sh self components or you know open
source components can you please define
that for us yeah I think that's a really
good foundation to start with and I
think the simplest way to understand
this is by first kind of defining and
understanding software ownership and so
I like to break that down into kind of
three distinct categories first second
and third party components so first
party components are any part or module
of software which you custom develop
inhouse as an organization it's often
referred to to is proprietary software a
second party is also considered
internally developed but maybe it comes
from a different part of business which
is legally separate so part of your
business that operates in a different
country or region of the world or part
of your business that is owned by or
operated as a wholly owned subsidiary
and then you have third party components
and that's anything that's truly
external to your business so maybe
that's software developed by an open
source maintainer as you mentioned or or
maybe some type of other thirdparty cont
contractor or vendor now commercial
offthe shelf software sometimes you'll
he hear it as kind of people refer to it
as it's acronym costs is software that
can be made up of any combination of
those types of components first second
or third party but the distinction that
makes CS unique is that it's made
available for purchase through some type
of public Marketplace which is why it's
referred to as commercial but also that
it's ready for use without any intensive
manual modification or or coding which
is where the term offthe shelf comes
from so essentially it's software that
anyone can buy and use almost
immediately without any major
customization that's great in fact I
think I learned something new today I
didn't realize that even the components
that we use from another subsidiary
could also be considered as externally
up but that does make sense so thank you
for that now the next question I have is
do you have any numbers for us for how
much percentage of an Enterprise
inventory is made up of third party comp
confidence this is a tough question and
I think you'll start to see my maybe
Consulting background emerge here in
this answer but ultimately it depends
and I say that because it depends on the
Strategic direction of the business that
is publishing or operating this software
I've worked with a number of companies
who have formally adopted this kind of
build first mentality in which they
believe they have the the Technical
Resources and knowhow internally where
they can develop their own software
that's attuned to their very specific
business requirements and they they
truly believe that their own development
will actually drive a competitive
advantage in the market I've also worked
with organizations who have adopted a
buy first mentality and that essentially
means that they have a desire to get
their product or service to Market as
quickly as possible and so they've
strategically decided upfront we're
going to buy whatever software our
business needs to accomplish that that
market presence faster so I've seen
organizations on broadly on both sides
of the spectrum some with 90% costs some
with 90% custom developed or open source
so I don't have an average number for
you unfortunately but that being said we
do have some insight into the makeup of
a traditional cot package that is
actually used within Enterprise
environments so synopsis does this
report every year it's called their osra
report it's the state of open- source
security and risk analysis and in last
year's reports they analyzed a number of
commercial caces across 15 or more
Industries and what they found was that
96 % of all kind of modern software
packages contained at least one
component and even more interestingly
76% so more than three4 of the modern
application is actually made up of Open
Source software so even within
commercial software we still see this
heavy Reliance on open source which is
ultimately being bundled into commercial
products which are being sold that's
very interesting I I'll make sure that I
add a link to that reference in our show
notes the next question is so why is
third party software supply chain
security important and why should I care
about it I think the importance of third
party software security comes back to
the simple fact of like we just talked
about whether you decide to buy it or
whether you decide to build it yourself
as an Enterprise if you are entrusting a
piece of software with some type of
sensitive information that could be your
own intellectual property it could be
pii so personally identifiable
information of your own employees or
even pii or sensitive financial
information of your customers you as a
business are solely responsible for that
decision of putting that data into that
application and protecting it
accordingly and so in the event of a
breach of that software and that data
you put into it yes you can maybe point
the finger at a vendor or an open source
maintainer and say it was their fault
but ultimately you as a business will
face Downstream impact of that breach so
that can come in the form of regulatory
fine an insurance claim a brand and
reputation damage and and that's not
just me saying that all of these risks
we've seen come to realization in in a
number of recent attacks the one I like
using for example as of recent is the
Move It software breach for example we
don't remember that attack campaign
because of the publisher I think a lot
of people aren't actually aware of the
vendor that publishes Move It software
we remember it because of the hundreds
of Downstream customers that were
impacted whose brand was kind of
plastered all over the front page of a
media Outlet because they trusted this
third party with their own company or
even customer data for secure file
transfer in that case and so that's why
it's so important to have these robust
third party risk processes to ensure
that the software that you rely on and
put your data into is secure not only
before you deploy it but that also
throughout that entirety of the life
cycle so any time that software changes
as well yeah so I think while you were
giving us this example I also remembered
when I was doing the research for this
show that I was reading this article
about from Gartner which predicts that
by 2025 45% of the organizations
worldwide will have experience attacks
on their software supply chain so yeah
and I think that is something that
you've just kind of brought to light
with that example so therefore in this
regard you talked about risk management
so how important is for an Enterprise
their risk management function risk
management is very broad term right
every Enterprise has a risk management
function and we'll get into it maybe
even a little bit later about what that
entails but for now if we stay into the
context of securing third party software
I'd say riskmanagement functions are
broadly responsible for a couple things
first at a very high level they need to
establish policies procedures controls
that govern third-party applications
throughout that life cycle of use like I
mentioned so prior to onboarding prior
to deployment and and future releases of
that software the second would be
ensuring adequate technology is actually
made available to the first line of
defense so those security practitioners
that are defending the business every
day to ensure that software that's
actually purchased by the organization
is abiding by those policies and
procedures that are established in the
first place and then finally and I guess
a lot more generally they're responsible
for making sure that any risks that are
found through the creation of policies
actual testing to make sure that they're
aligning to policies need to be managed
within the bounds of the risk appetite
or the risk thresholds that that
Enterprise risk management function sets
in accordance with business risk
appetite as well yeah that's actually uh
quite a lot and seems quite interesting
as well so like a lot of companies also
seem to have this program called the
third party risk management so I guess
this is what they do right this function
is essentially looking at all the third
parties coming in okay exactly and a lot
of people will refer to it as third
party risk management tprm if you hear
that term as well and the easiest way I
like to kind of explain tprm is through
the the saying that you'll often hear is
no man is an island right no business
can operate in today's world without
Outsourcing certain aspects of your
people your process or your technology
so in in very simple terms the basic
function of tprm is to understand and
manage the risk that's presented by any
external party which your business
relies on to operate and the one thing
to keep in mind when talking about tprm
is the the way tprm programs
traditionally identify and measure
security risk is through the the kind of
notorious vendor questionnaire right I'm
sure a lot of your corporate listeners
have likely dealt with it from one side
or the another where you have an Excel
sheet that's shared over email or
through GRC that no one wants to receive
right it's probably anywhere from 50 to
250 questions but the aim of those
questionnaires is mainly to understand
what is the security posture of of
policies procedures and controls within
the vendor environment and that's where
it gets really interesting in my opinion
especially in the context of today's
discussion because when you talk about
thirdparty software tprm teams have kind
of viewed the vendors of commercial
off-the-shelf software products as
actually outside of their own oversight
agreement so they don't believe that
they're responsible for overseeing them
and that's because commercial off the
shelf software isn't operated within the
vendor environment which is what a
questionnaire would capture it's
actually handed over in binary format to
the Enterprise that purchases it to be
deployed and independently managed in
their technology stack and then beyond
that they don't have access to customer
data they don't have connectivity to the
corporate Network so in a vacuum that
that vendor relationship seemingly holds
no risk so there's no reason for tprm to
oversee it now we know that's not true
right because we've seen all these
products exploited successfully between
solar winds COV CA and many others so
for the past couple years we know that
there is this clear hole that exists in
the way that software supply chain risk
has been managed especially from a tprm
capability and unfortunately as a result
a lot of risk has slipped through the
crack so tprm is very easy to Define as
a function it's in my opinion very
difficult to successfully deliver
especially when you're considering those
the intricacies that are posed by the
the software supply chain that's really
interesting so what should the companies
protect so if I get when I'm evaluating
a third party software risk is it the
package to make sure that that's well
protected or well It ultimately depends
right there are a number of risks that
are presented by a third party cyber
security isn't the only risk there's
privacy risk there's ESG risk there's
Financial viability risk right the risk
that one of your vendors goes in solvent
and can no longer provide that product
or service to you now all those things
need to be considered when deciding
whether to Outsource a function so the
risk though presented to an organization
will ultimately depend on the third
party type and so will the way that you
manage that risk so I'll give an example
a commercial off-the-shelf software
supplier is very different from that of
a professional service provider like a
consultancy because a consultancy is
providing augmented staff or additional
people and a software vendor is
providing an actual product so the
biggest piece of advice I give when kind
of discussing how to effectively manage
third parties is resist the the natural
urge to adapt that one siiz fits-all
mentality and and make sure that the
risk management activities that you
actually perform on that vendor are
specific to the actual product or
service that you consume so for software
suppliers like you said yes that means
looking at the security and integrity of
the software at the actual binary level
because that's where the risk exists for
that vendor where it resides for that
vendor versus that consultancy example
we talked about maybe you're looking
deeper at hiring or background check or
termination processes because the
service you're consuming is people it's
augmented staff so the point is risk is
going to differ across every different
vendor that you operate with so the
oversights and risk management
activities that you should be performing
should be unique to that the product or
service that the vendor provides okay
that's very interesting and you're right
about the one siiz fits all I think
that's there are a lot of places where
we try to take that approach because
it's easy when to set it up right yeah
yeah it's not just me saying that too we
have like oversight bodies that say that
so I'm based out of London and we have
the national cyber security Center ncsc
and they have guidance over vendor risk
management and one of the things that
they say is exactly that don't provide
this one-size fits-all creat a
thirdparty risk program which is catered
to supplier types so it's not just me on
my horse saying it there's there's other
oversite body saying that as well okay
so let's like move on to the next
section where we'll do a little bit of a
deep dive into to some of these Concepts
so now when you have this kind of
software supply chain are there like
personas like a producer and a consumer
and what are their responsibilities
maybe that we could kind of Define for
us yeah sure so I'd say there's probably
two main stakeholder groups that that
traditionally come up when we talk about
software supply chain security
especially when we're talking about it
within the the context of Enterprise
security risk management so the first
would be Publishers of software those
are organizations that develop and sell
software so if you think about the
microsofts the oracles the Adobes of the
world and then there's Enterprise
consumers of software so organizations
who procure deploy software to operate a
certain aspect of their business now in
reality yes there's a number of other
stakeholders between open source
maintainers and resellers and
Distributors that make up that broader
ecosystem but Publishers and consumers
are in my opinion the main stakeholder
groups because they often are the only
ones that have formal requirements that
are levied upon them by bodies like
legislators and Regulators as well and
so in this case I wanted to ask you like
what are the you know process for
identifying the security supply chain
risks so so you have a publisher
producing something so how do I go ahead
and you know what's the process for
identifying the things is this something
that's run from the tpr program by based
on the guidance or how does one start
managing this I guess it depends on the
Persona right so for Publishers you have
everything from the creation of source
code and making sure that source code is
securely built and designed you have the
integration of third-party components
through your cicd pipeline making sure
that the the sources that you're pulling
those components from are secure and
they're not masquerading as fake ones
essentially or they're fake components
Mas raing as legitimate components you
have the compilation of all of those
source code into binary format and all
the inclusion of additional components
that get added making sure it's safe
before you publish it so doing a final
build exam essentially on the publisher
side and then you have the release of it
to the customer or the consumer of
software and then on the consumer you
have a separate set of checks so it's
rather than a final release exam it's a
final deployment exam so before I bring
the software into my environment I need
to test it to make sure it's secure and
offload my responsibility
and then for every update thereafter I
need to make sure that that update is
secure so all the patches hot fixes
feature releases those kinds of things
and then I need to continually monitor
that software throughout its life cycle
looking for either emerging risks and
threats in new components that are added
or old components that were legitimate
and safe at one time that are no longer
safe the log for JS of the world and
whatnot so it really depends on the
Persona that you're talking about and
how they need to manage it and the stage
of the life cycle that that it sits in
so I was just wondering now one of the
things we could do is probably look at
some you know case study where things
went wrong and we had another Show
episode 535 where they went through the
solar wind attack as well as the Cod go
there's this other attack with the 3cx
and is that something that you can take
us through and tell us what happened and
how do maybe organizations protect
themselves yeah 3cx is a really
interesting one because it's probably
the first exam example we've broadly
seen in the industry of what we're
calling a cascading supply chain attack
so those who aren't familiar with 3cx
they're a software publisher they had
one of their Flagship products a desktop
phone software breached mandiant was
brought in after the attack to perform
an investigation to find out what what
happened what they found was that the
initial breach of 3cx actually occurred
because an employee had without
permission downloaded some third party
software package that wasn't relevant to
their job role it was ANC called X
Trader that application had a back door
within embedded within it which allowed
malicious actors into their environment
once breached attackers then infiltrated
the build pipeline of 3cx inserted
malware into the product and then used
their release process as a as a way to
distributes that malware down to all the
downstream customers of 3cx so in a
vacuum some may view that as as a
failure by the publisher to kind of fail
or secure the sdlc process like we
talked about on the if we talk about
controls between the publisher and the
consumer but in my opinion I think it's
more important to actually recognize
that the root of the attack actually
stems back to the importance of making
sure that all software is tested before
it's either allowed into your network or
onto an Enterprise asset like a an
employee desktop or a developer desktop
in this case so it shows that yes even
if you're a publisher those publisher
controls are important but if you're a
publisher you're likely also consumer of
software so it's just as important to
protect your third party and Commercial
software estate as it's the own software
that you are developing inhouse that's I
think yeah very very insightful so the
thing is now so you said two things like
for an organization to protect
themselves from this type of attack is
one is of course protecting what you're
building and also I think look very
clearly into like your developer
machines and things like that and make
sure that attack Vector is also plugged
so the term you use cascading attack
could you again explain that to me so
this is an example like I mean is there
a way to define it and other examples
it's a relatively new term so I'd
probably summarize it as a double supply
chain attack where the initial entry
point of an attack is through the
consumption of third-party software like
in 3cx his case it was this x Trader
application so it's targeting a single
user which in turn results in the
compromise of a much more widely used
package with the ultimate goal of
reaching thousands or hundreds of
thousands of Downstream customers so it
creates this kind of I know I'm using
the term again but cascading attack path
that's expanding Downstream within the
software supply chain so the one of the
things is of course there's this secure
software development framework that was
created by nist to handle supply chain
risks is that something that you can
Define for our I mean at least give us a
overview not defined but maybe overview
of what that is and what should
organizations be looking at that and
adopting
yeah so nist actually has a special
publication series which provides
technical guidance on a number of
specific security domains and topics so
ssdf is nist special publication 8218
the secure software development
framework it was published last February
so just over a year ago now but it
provides a set of kind of 40 best
practice controls which they call tasks
to enable secure software development
and so for any organization that
provides software
to a US government agency they must now
complete a written attestation so they
must on paper say that they meet the
standards which are defined within ssdf
all 40 of those practices and that's
applicable to any new software that's
built any major version changes to
existing software that's already
provided or in the terms of like a
contract renewal with the US government
and if they don't meet those
requirements it doesn't mean that they
can't continue to provide that software
it just means that they need to to
Simply provide their plans to address
and remediate any of the shortcomings
that exist within that framework as I
listen to your talk from RSA 2023 and
you made a comment on this software
development framework I mean there's a
certain limitation that is you said the
presence of a vulnerability does not
indicate that a software package has
been compromised and presents immediate
threat to publishing or inquiring
organization can you explain that yes
it's an issue that I've been pretty
public about with that I have with ssdf
and I've actually we've shared with n
directly through various feedback
mechanisms but it's this kind of
hyperfocus that not only ssdf but other
Frameworks have out there on
vulnerability detection and
vulnerability management and I pick on
ssdf because more than 50% of those
practices that we talked about focus on
either the protection the identification
or the remediation of vulnerabilities
within s software and although yes
detection and Remediation of
vulnerabilities is absolutely critical
to uplifting the security posture of
software the presence of those
vulnerabilities doesn't provide a really
strong indication that a package has
been compromised or like you said
presents an immediate threat to a
publisher or a consumer I don't want to
mix up my words because there's no doubt
that vulnerabilities are important piece
of the puzzle to solving the software
supply chain and I don't think I want to
argue that but I think that the overly
targeted prioritization of
vulnerabilities doesn't quite match up
with the reality of the threat landscape
because we see a number of these
techniques that are being kind of
actively leveraged in successful attacks
which aren't leveraging known cbes like
solar winds and the 3cx example we just
talked about and so in my personal
opinion I think if nist really wants to
take a risk-based approach to managing
software security they should shift
their focus from vulnerability identif
ification to identification of kind of
known malicious components or known
malware strains that exist within
software which is a much better
indicator that a breach has occurred or
that an attack is ongoing within an
organization it's interesting because
while you were talking I was thinking
about the time when the log 4J patching
happened right and I think a lot the
teams were like really confused because
the thing is that the communication that
came out just kept rapidly changing so
because you you didn't know this patch
work the next patch work and finally
there were certain cases where some
teams were not even affected by the
vulnerability but they just had to patch
you know and there was a lot of problems
because of that so what turned out to be
like a 3-day Affair actually turned out
to be like 15 or 20 days of work and
that's honestly why I think it gets
vulnerabilities get so much attention
and so much of the Frameworks are made
up by vulnerability related controls
because you have these celebrity
vulnerabilities like log 4J that get
Amplified in the media when in reality
yes it is a massive problem and it had a
huge impact across the security
community and organizations but if you
look at the I guess number of attacks
that are occurring so our threat
research team internally did a study
last year where they were looking at
software supply chain attacks within the
open source Community specifically and
within a few of the kind of major
package managers so I think it was npm
and piie the number of targeted or
malicious attacks we almost doubling the
number of attacks that used a cve or
known vulnerability as initial attack
Factor so yes the celebrity
vulnerabilities get a lot of attention
but it doesn't mean that it causes the
majority of issues we're seeing the
majority of issues actually come through
malware and or targeted attack so it's
worth spending time and effort in your
security program to protect against them
too okay thank you so let's move on to
another framework called the salsa
framework or SLS
can you tell us about that yes so salsa
supply chain levels for software
artifacts is what it stands for it's
just another framework that's published
and maintained specifically by op ssf
it's already been in use by Google for
various years but it's specifically
designed to help protect against
software supply chain attacks so it has
similarly a number of requirements and
controls like ssdf but it's actually
presented in a tiered model so the idea
is it's intended to promote security
regression over time but the reason I
like salsa is it also has in addition to
its requirements this kind of visual
threat model and it helps really
demonstrate the breadth of attack
techniques that could be used across the
software supply chain so it covers
everything from typo squatting attacks
and in the open source ecosystem to
tampering of build environments to
secret leakage so it does a really good
job of once again kind of coming back to
the main issue I have with ssdf is
showing that yes vulnerabilities are
important but it's truly just one
mechanism out of many that can be used
in an attack I think that's a good segue
to my next question which is like one of
the biggest assumptions when using open
source or say a third party components
is the trust bit which you said so is
there some guidance on how to trust for
example can you make a men vendor prove
that they use one of these Frameworks
and is that enough well trust is
something that everyone deals with right
first there's no shortage of Frameworks
out there which cover Supply chains
security salsa and ssdf which we just
talked about are just the very tip of
the iceberg in forcing your vendor to
prove compliance with one of those
Frameworks I think is a different thing
it's I think of trust just like in real
relationships digital trust isn't
something that can just be obtained or
imparted on someone it has to be earned
over time and unfortunately in the
Enterprise environment the ability to
validate that concept of trust as a
starting point in a relationship really
depends on how much much leverage you
have so for example the US government
now is enforcing ssdf like I said for
any software vendors of theirs they can
do that because they have the grand
power of legislation and they also have
a lot of buying power and then you also
have kind of some private sector
entities that have very mature Security
Programs and also significant buying
power if you think of like the large
financial institutions for example so
they also find ways of enforcing it
through a lot of times they'll amend
their standard Contracting terms to
require their organizations that they
work with if they want to have their
product purchased by them to maintain
higher development standards and they'll
include things like ssdf or salsa in
that or they'll include the requirement
to say I don't care what Frameworks that
you abide by I want the ability and the
right to test the software myself before
I purchase it so right now there's very
little concrete enforcement in the
industry but we're very quickly seeing
expectations start to ramp up because of
not only legislation and regulation
that's emerging but also independently
in the private sector as well okay so I
think maybe we'll cover that bit a
little bit more and we do this next
section on the legislation bit I have
one more question to ask which is
related to this thing called transitive
dependencies so when you use a third
party confident and that depends on many
other components and there's a problem
in like the components usage of other
third parties and then you're kind of
affected by that so how does this affect
the supply chain attacks and what can
you do because you can have a direct
relationship with the component that
you're using or even the vendor that
you're using but they are affected by
somebody else so how can you actually
have a seeing that that's always gets my
goat transitive dependencies is where it
start to get very complex I like to
think about transitive dependencies very
similar to the way that we think about
managing fourth fifth or what we call
kind of nth party risk in the in third
party risk space it's basically an
indirect dependency relationship which
is I know it's a bit of a mouthful so
the basic way I like to explain is
walking through an example if you have
three components a b and c you have
component a depending on component B
component B depending on component C so
you can say that there's a transitive
dependency between a and C as they're
indirectly linked through that middle
component B now to achieve that is
another thing I think It ultimately
requires a very very granular
understanding of not only the components
and dependencies which are embedded or
contained within a software package but
like you said also understanding what
Downstream dependencies those components
actually rely on to operate when the
software is being executed and running
in multiple environments which is a
tough problem to manage but I think
ultimately it comes back to having a
very comprehensive software inventory
for not only all the components you're
using internally but externally as well
and then regularly monitoring that
inventory to manage the risk of
transitive dependencies when you come
aware of new intelligence that may pose
a risk or may pose a threat yeah so can
you talk a little bit about that piece
on that visibility like so how do you
build that visibility of all that is it
through the s that inventory management
or is is a good tool yeah so visibility
is a big issue we here especially when
we talk about commercial software in the
security industry a lot of organizations
struggle to gain visibility for two main
reasons one unlike open source software
they don't have access to the underlying
source code so there's very few Tools in
their Arsenal that they can use to
perform testing and gain insights into
that package the second is they actually
don't have the contractual leverage to
enforce a vendor to provide them any
evidence or provide them any insight
into that software and that second one
is important because
we often forget that software contracts
are very different from that which
traditionally govern a normal Enterprise
relationship they're structured
differently they're written in the form
of a shrink wrap agreement or n user
licensing agreement so they don't have
standard terms like the right to audit
which would enable an Enterprise
customer to perform some proper due
diligence and understand what's in the
software and if it poses a risk so the
question becomes if you don't have any
visibility into kind of vendor security
process
or software itself what can you do and
that's where we really see kind of
binary analysis this concept of binary
analysis emerging as a really powerful
option for Enterprise consumers because
it essentially allows you to not only
generate an s bomb but also analyze the
risk presented by all those components
and dependencies within the sbom just
using the binary itself so without any
underlying access to the source code
needed and that's extremely powerful
because then you can start shedding that
dependency on your vendor to provide
evidence
and you can start empowering yourself to
independently evaluate whether you can
trust not only that software but all the
components and dependencies which are
listed in the sbom which make it up okay
that's interesting so the thing I wanted
to ask you is obviously sometimes your
dependencies could run into like
hundreds or maybe thousands but so then
to do this binary analysis like that
becomes a bit expensive right so would
automation help in such cases or yes so
automation is absolutely needed I think
when you think about the breadth of
supply chain and complexities of the
kind of modern commercial software
package which like you said it could be
made up of not tens of components but
hundreds of thousands of components and
dependencies themselves the task of
understanding it securing it managing it
is simply too large to achieve manually
so if you want to effectively manage
that risk at scale it has to be done in
some autom fashion so I think relying on
technology to help offload basic things
like Risk analysis not doing like
manually reverse engineering I think
that's vitally important if you want to
achieve success in a security program
especially when talking about the
software supply chain yes so so maybe
now I can kind of ask you like if I were
Tove back into the third party risks
right what are the steps that then the
third party risk team should do when you
know evaluating this component which has
so many dependencies is there I mean I
guess one of the things you said the
checklist is not a really great thing
but are there any steps that they should
be following on what they should be
doing the binary analysis on or what
parts they should focus on it starts
with some very basic foundations like
understanding who your software
suppliers are that may seem like an
obvious thing to do but you'd be amazed
by the number of kind of Fortune 500 or
Global 10,000 firms that have very
mature Security Programs and struggle to
answer that very foundational question
the second thing would be once you
understand who you're working with and
what software or other vendor or third
party services that you're consuming
understanding which of those suppliers
present the highest risk to your
business you can't overse everyone so
you need to figure out who to Target and
so you can do that by thinking about a
number of kind of inherent risk criteria
that would pose risk to your business so
are they supporting a critical or
important business process or for
software are they connected or
considered even Crown jeel systems
within your business and then finally
once you understand who your software
suppliers are you've put them neatly
into risk buckets critical high medium
low establishing some sort of consistent
testing methodology that you can
evaluate each of those on based on the
risk that they actually pose to your
business so maybe for software suppliers
that means before deployments and after
every new version of software released
you're testing X Y and Z and then maybe
you don't deploy that software if
certain things are found like if I find
malware present within my software it is
an absolute no-o I will break the build
I will not ship it or I will not deploy
it or if I find a critical risk
vulnerability that's being actively
exploited and known therefore posted in
the sisa Kev catalog and then making
sure those issues are documented and
mitigated obviously so to summarize
three steps
understand who your suppliers are risk
rank them and then apply some repeatable
testing methodology based on risk okay
so suppose now the third party function
has actually gone ahead and done these
things and they tell me that this CS
either the software is fit to use or the
component is fit to use as well if I'm
using it as part of something larger
then is it good enough do I need to also
reassess it periodically yeah the short
answer is no it's not good enough
and I say that because once again if we
think about this in the context of
broader tprm program software vendor
relationships are very different than
that of a traditional Enterprise
relationship that we may think about
it's not like a BP an outsourced
business process let's say back office
accounting for example where the
function or the nature of the service
never actually changes after you onboard
them it's the same from onboarding to
offboarding software is very Dynamic it
constantly Chang es and so when a new
version of software is released your
whole risk profile or the whole risk
profile that's presented by the vendor
can change if the underlying components
dependencies or versions of any of those
change as well so no a single point in
time is not enough it should be
regularly reviewed throughout the life
cycle of the package and so that means I
guess that that is one thing so if there
is obviously a cost associated with this
I think that's something that we never
really think about when we actually do a
t-shirt sizing that's maybe that's
something I just stly think about that
maybe that's something that we need to
also put in when we deliver software
right so I guess the upper management is
also aware of that that there is this
risk of when we use the software
component or this thing there's also the
maintenance cost there absolutely yeah
so I was going to ask you as a consumer
like in this if you were to look at the
State of Affairs today are there any
existing problems in the way we are
evaluating our software anything else
that you know strikes you that you think
that business should know about yeah a
few that we already talked about things
like the lack of visibility into
software which is a mix of it's the
reason that visibility doesn't exist
like we talked about contract
limitations or the push back on the
perceived invasive nature of testing for
that vendor things like the lack of
scalability where most traditional
process are largely manual driven
through things like vendor question
errors or manual testing but another
thing that we really see emerging is
this growing concern over the level of
assurance that can actually be derived
from these traditional testing methods
like questionnaires because they're
ultimately based on self attestation
from the vendor like ssdf for example
like if someone's providing software to
the US government they have to self
attest that they're meeting these
requirements so in other words they are
telling you how secure they are based on
interviews they provide based on
evidence they curate so it doesn't
really provide a true representation of
risk and so as a result we're seeing a
lot of professionals kind of scrambling
to look for other ways to achieve
Assurance as a result of that okay so I
think one of the things I learned today
was also about this binary analysis I
think that's probably a good tool to use
in Your Arsenal right apart from this
questionnaire and I'm sure there are
other things but I think that would be
one good thing or would you say like I
mean I think that's one thing that just
stayed with me but is there anything
else newer way of doing things yeah I
think binary analysis is a really
interesting one and Gartner actually put
it really interesting in a recent
analysis report they did over commercial
software risk which I'm glad to share
with everyone but they ultimately framed
binary analysis as a way for Enterprise
consumers to confirm documentation
that's provided by the vendor which is a
really interesting way I think of
putting it so not solely relying on what
they're telling you but validating it
yourself and maybe I can even give a
quick example example of how binary
analysis works for people that aren't
familiar but essentially it takes a
fully compiled binary package so one
that you may purchase off a vendor
website it deconstructs it without any
manual kind of preper manipulation
required and then it takes all of the
objects which it's extracted so yes
components and dependencies which may be
listed in a standard as bomb but also
think about all those other embedded
objects which may rely or may exist
within a p package device drivers
installation files embedded images
whatever they may be and then it
analyzes them for risk and threats and
it's traditionally done not only through
binary analysis but also layering things
with file and reputation Services threat
intelligence feeds other Technologies
like Ai and machine learning that's when
you can start to do some really cool
stuff to understand can you not only
trust a package but all the underlying
objects which exist within it and then
once again finally putting that neatly
all together in an sbom so it's not just
binary analysis it's a lot of this other
types of technology that you need to
kind of layer it together with to not
only understand what's in your software
that you publish or consume so it's
actually useful for both personas but
then once again what is the risk that it
presents because es bombs only take you
so far right they tell you what's in
your software you need to understand if
if that presents a risk or a threat to
your business or your customers B
interesting so I think makes sense that
now that we've covered a lot of this
that we talk a little bit about the laws
and regulation so can you talk us
through this because one of the things
is what are the laws and regulations in
this space that companies need to adhere
to it's funny I get this question
probably the most frequently out of any
and I feel like it's because there's a
new law or regulatory requirement that
pops up every day after the back of a
new attack so we have the obvious ones
that I'm sure people have talked about
at nauseum things like the initial
executive order 1428 that was published
by Joe Biden US Government you also have
the White House memo 201218 that
followed that those are mainly focused
on software suppliers providing products
and services to the US government like
we talked about but in the US you also
have industry specific regulations like
that from the FDA which enforce stricter
requirements on software that's embedded
within medical devices you also have a
number of regulations emerging in Europe
things like the Cyber resilience act
that covers commercial software
Publishers in Europe you also have
regulations on the consumer side in
Europe so the digital operational
resilience act you'll often hear it
referred to as Dora that specifically
applies to financial entities in Europe
which are consuming commercial software
and the expectations of those financial
entities to protect against attacks on
those and then you also have
requirements emerging in regions like
APAC so you have the monetory authority
of Singapore they have technology risk
management guidelines which has a whole
section on their expectations on
software supply chain risks very
specifically so a number of emerging
laws and regulations all either in
effect or coming into effect very soon
so for like cyber resilience act and
Dora those come into effect within the
next 12 months for example okay well so
I think what would be interesting for us
listeners is also would you have some
examples if it's okay to share where
violations of these laws caused
significant damage yeah so solar winds
is probably the one that gets the most
attention because of the charges of
Fraud and the ongoing actions that are
being taken by the SEC right now so I
won't spend too much time on that but I
think another interesting one we briefly
discussed before was for the move it
application so I didn't go into it in
too much detail but for those listeners
who aren't familiar move it a file
transfer application it's published by
progress software it had a critical
severity vulnerability that was being
actively exploited within it by a
ransomware group called Klo and they
ultimately got a hold of a very large
volume of Downstream customer data and
as a result of that breach progress
who's the publisher of software has not
only an ongoing investigation from the
SEC very similar to solar winds they
have more than 20 customers that are
seeking indemnification from the attack
they have insurance providers who are
seeking separate compensation for being
essentially the at fault party
as a part of the publisher consumer
relationship and then on top of that
they have like more than I think it's 50
plus class action lawsuits from
individuals that are claiming to be
affected by this data extortion so we
can very quickly see that this isn't
like a hypothetical Threat Vector that
holds potential risk it's it's very real
and it can cause very substantial not
only financial but reputational impact
as well so actually so the I think this
clearly demonstrates that if you don't
look at your your third party this which
you actually are not you don't don't
directly own even then you're kind of
accountable if things go wrong
absolutely and it's starting to be
looked at as negligent essentially in
the legislative and Regulatory realm as
you said even if it's not your own
software it's thirdparty software
because goes back to an earlier point
but you have made a decision
strategically as a business to not
develop it inhouse to Outsource it so
you're still responsible for protecting
it in that capacity yeah so I think I'll
think about this the next time I pick a
package where I'm just doing a pip
install and was like okay yeah I think
it does really make sense I would
actually like to kind of close this
session with maybe one last thing I want
to ask in your opinion what are the top
three things that companies or maybe
even individuals should do to protect
themselves from software supply chain
ATT TS yeah I mean it may seem
repetitive but think it goes back to
foundational security there's nothing
incredibly complex that you need to do
out there but I think it first starts
with understanding the software that
you're using understanding which of that
software presents the most risk to you
because you're not going to be able to
oversee or test or inquire about all of
it and you can do that using some of
those inherent risk characteristics that
we talked about and then finally and
most importantly thinking about what are
those repeatable stage Gates for testing
that most critical software that you can
deploy throughout the entire life cycle
of use so you can actually establish
trust with it before using it and then
we actually talked about it too but
making sure that last step that testing
is actually supported by some level of
Technology some level of automation so
that you can actually keep Pace with the
speed of Business Without impeding or
impacting operations so we want to be
viewed in security as a value enabler
not a value protector right so how do
you keep Pace with business while still
protecting your business
accordingly I I guess you know I did say
it was the one last question but based
on what you said are there any tools
that you're aware of that can support
this testing or is it just the things
that we've already used just for like
testing the softare it's a lot of the
things that we've talked about I mean
ultimately it depends on the Persona you
are and the life cycle stage that you're
in as a developer or consumer right
there's tool tools that look at source
code there are tools that look at the
evaluation of packages as they come
through your pipeline there's tools that
you can only look at when you're about
to ship that final package because it's
in a binary format right so it just
ultimately depends where you are trying
to get Assurance over the software that
you're building I typically suggest
starting with a very final stage right
before you're about to ship something
because that's the simplest but over
time like there's always that concept
can you shift left into your development
Pipeline and find issues earlier but
it's all about understanding where you
are in your maturity life cycle and
figuring that out and then what the
needs of your business are ultimately
makes one think that if you really don't
require a package it's probably you're
better off just not using it just don't
get unnecessary packages I think that's
another thing as a developer and also
remember we did this other episode on
obfuscation and there was an interesting
question that I posted to the guest
there Professor Ross Anderson and he I
think I I I remember asking him so
should I would it be better off if he
you know write the code ourselves then
actually get a third party confident and
he was like he said yeah maybe in a lot
of cases you're better off doing that
you know then then actually bringing it
up because there's a lot of these
factors and now talking with you I think
I can see a lot of the regulatory
aspects as well so yeah I think there's
lots to think about as an Enterprise on
software supply chain So yeah thank you
for this of course it was a very fun
session yeah okay and I guess Before I
Let You Go there's one question on best
way for people to reach you in the cyber
space would that be yeah I'm always
active on LinkedIn I post quite a bit of
kind of educational or content or
thought leadership surrounding software
supply chain security more generally so
please don't hesitate to reach out and
connect I'd love to continue this
conversation this is great thanks for
coming on the show charie thanks for
having me it was a lot of fun this is
Priyanka ran for software engineering
radio thanks for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team e-r.
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]